<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<schedule>
<!-- ************************ OPENING PLENARY ****************** -->
  <session>
    <time>8:30</time>
    <room_id>3</room_id>
    <title>Registration</title>
    <teaser>Pick up your nametag at the registration desk.</teaser>
    <body><![CDATA[<p>Pick up your nametag at the registration desk by the Hall of Service.</p> 
      ]]></body>
  </session>
  <session>
    <time>9:30</time>
    <room_id>1</room_id>
    <title>Welcome</title>
    <teaser>Kick off FedGeoDay 2016.</teaser>
    <body><![CDATA[<p>A brief welcome to FedGeoDay 2016</p> 
      ]]></body>
  </session>
<!-- ************************ OPENING PLENARY ****************** -->
  <session>
    <time>9:40</time>
    <room_id>1</room_id>
    <title>Keynote: TBD</title>
    <teaser>Ray Bauer, Innovation Lead at NGA, teaser TBD</teaser>
    <body><![CDATA[<p>
description TBD
</p>
      ]]></body>
  </session>
<!-- ************************ BREAK TIME ****************** -->
  <session>
    <time>10:30</time>
    <room_id>3</room_id>
    <title>Break</title>
    <teaser>Refreshments served outside the hall of service.</teaser>
    <body><![CDATA[<p>Refreshments served outside the hall of service</p>
      ]]></body>
  </session>
<!-- ************************ BREAK TIME ****************** -->
  <session>
    <time>10:45</time>
    <room_id>1</room_id>
    <title>Open Publishing: How the FCC Empowered Map Publishing with Open Source Technologies and Standards</title>
    <teaser>Allison Baker &amp; Brian Funk, teaser TBD.</teaser>
    <body><![CDATA[<p>
Allison Baker, product owner for this effort, drove the redesign of FCC Maps with an emphasis on rapid publication. Brian Funk designed the architecture for FCC Maps and led the development team. Together, we will present an overview of the FCC’s new map publishing platform empowering users by integrating open source technologies (Drupal, GeoServer, Node.js) with open standards (OGC).</p>
      ]]></body>
  </session>
  <session>
    <time>10:45</time>
    <room_id>2</room_id>
    <title>Understanding Open Source</title>
    <teaser>Jody Garnett, Community Lead at Boundless, explains how government can benefit from participation in open source.</teaser>
    <body><![CDATA[<p> 
      Open source is gleefully rewriting the rules of IT development at all levels of industry and government. Adoption of open source in government is well underway, with success stories  illustrating the benefits. This decade we are going further - fostering a healthy, sustainable, working relationship between government and open source:
* This presentation digs into the flexibility of open source licensing and how government organizations can meet the challenges of developing with open source. 
* We will look at the advantages of government participation in open source at the project, institutional, and foundation level. 
Attend this talk to understand how your organization cannot only benefit from open source, but be open source.</p>
      ]]></body>
  </session>
  <session>
    <time>11:15</time>
    <room_id>1</room_id>
    <title>Geography for HIV Epidemic Control: PEPFAR’s use of open source geospatial tools</title>
    <teaser>Nate Heard &amp; Gina Sarfaty, teaser TBD</teaser>
    <body><![CDATA[<p>
The U.S. President's Emergency Plan for AIDS Relief (PEPFAR) is the U.S. Government initiative to help save the lives of those affected by HIV/AIDS around the world. PEPFAR has a data-driven focus that strategically aligns community and clinical services with targeted geographic areas to achieve a greater impact on the epidemic. Understanding spatial variation of HIV-affected populations and where PEPFAR supports service delivery is key to geographic prioritization.
 
PEPFAR manages multiple data streams, including epidemiology, demography, program indicator and budget data. The spatial data infrastructure that enables analysts to map these data spans all 36 PEPFAR country and regional programs and includes geographic coordinates for most clinical sites. PEPFAR leverages this system for improved spatial targeting of HIV treatment and prevention services. As a result of the adoption of a geographically-informed, data-driven approach PEPFAR has set a target to support a total of 12.9 million people on life-saving anti-retroviral treatment by the end of 2017.
 
This talk provides an overview of PEPFAR’s use of open source tools such as QGIS, GeoNode, and DATIM, an open source, web-based health information system that includes GIS. We’ll describe successes and challenges in our work to leverage geography for global HIV epidemic control.​
</p>
      ]]></body>
  </session>
  <session>
    <time>11:15</time>
    <room_id>2</room_id>
    <title>Institutional engagement in an open mapping community</title>
    <teaser>Dan Joseph, teaser TBD</teaser>
    <body><![CDATA[<p>
The American Red Cross, as a founding member of the Missing Maps initiative, is actively working to map 200 million of the world’s vulnerable people into OpenStreetMap (OSM) by 2021; creating open map data for anyone to access, use, and update. This past year, the activities included our biggest field effort to date: launching a mapping hub in West Africa and training local volunteers to field map over 5,000 villages in the border regions of Liberia, Guinea, and Sierra Leone.

The remote areas in which Red Cross works are full of technical challenges: no connectivity, extremely poor roads, lack of electricity, dispersed volunteers, etc. A combination of high- and low-tech tools facilitate field mapping. Our preferred tool is an Android app. However, when conditions necessitate alternative methods we can deploy handheld GPS devices and paper-based mapping tools. Also, the American Red Cross has developed POSM, an offline server that facilitates field mapping in areas without an internet connection for upwards of a month.

In addition to its own disaster response and internal program activities, the American Red Cross collaborates with US government entities such as MapGive and HIU, as well as the CDC. This talk will explore the how and why of American Red Cross’ commitment to open data, open source tools, and community engagement to map vulnerable communities around the world.
</p>
      ]]></body>
  </session>
<!-- ************************ LUNCH TIME ****************** -->
  <session>
    <time>11:45</time>
    <room_id>3</room_id>
    <title>Lunch</title>
    <teaser>Lunch will be served outside the session rooms.</teaser>
    <body><![CDATA[<p>Lunch will be served outside the hall of service. menu TBD</p>
      ]]></body>
  </session>
<!-- ************************ LUNCH TIME ****************** -->
  <session>
    <time>13:00</time>
    <room_id>1</room_id>
    <title>Thinking Open – A Hybrid Approach to GIS</title>
    <teaser>Anthony Calamito, Federal CTO at Boundless, teaser TBD</teaser>
    <body><![CDATA[<p>
As open-source technology trends continue to emerge in modern IT enterprises, there has been significant interest from the geospatial community in implementing open-source GIS technologies.  There are a multitude of reasons why organizations consider open-source, and in this discussion, Boundless will share best practices around a hybrid approach to integrating and implementing open-source geospatial technologies, alongside existing proprietary technologies and tools.   And rather than rip-and-replace your existing software for open source, this talk will describe how to gradually migrate portions of your enterprise at a time.</p>
      ]]></body>
  </session>
    <session>
    <time>13:00</time>
    <room_id>2</room_id>
    <title>Creating an Open, Global Shoreline Service</title>
    <teaser>Carter Christopher, TBD at NGA, teaser TBD</teaser>
    <body><![CDATA[<p>
RadiantBlue Technologies is developing an open-source-software-based system for generating an automated, global coastline service. The system incorporates data from multiple commercial satellite imagery sources, and runs feature detection algorithms to produce new coastline GIS/vector data as the imagery is collected.  The system will serve Geospatial Analysts, Intelligence Analysts, and Feature Data Managers as a resource for utilizing detection algorithms to delineate feature data from unclassified imagery.  The system provides new and exciting opportunities in the areas of maritime navigation, sovereign borders awareness, and disaster relief/assessment in coastal and port areas of the world.
</p>
      ]]></body>
  </session>

  <session>
    <time>13:30</time>
    <room_id>1</room_id>
    <title>DoD and IC Geospatial Standards Compliance</title>
    <teaser>Jeffrey Bell - National GEOINT Officer for Standards, NGA, teaser TBD</teaser>
    <body><![CDATA[
<p>
This session is a short talk covering the National System for Geospatial Intelligence (NSG) GEOINT Functional Manager Standards Assessment (GFMSA) Program.  The program, established by the National Geospatial-Intelligence Agency (NGA) as the Functional Manager for GEOINT Standards in the IC and DoD, provisions a GEOINT Standards compliance process that advances GEOINT interoperability, understand and sharing across the NSG in the area of data, services, sensors, and imagery.  The talk will cover the process as well as benefits and use cases for standards compliance and non-compliance.
</p>
      ]]></body>
  </session>
  <session>
    <time>13:30</time>
    <room_id>2</room_id>
    <title>Billions and Beyond: Analyzing and Visualizing Massive Datasets</title>
    <teaser>Rich Fecher, Software Developer, Radiant Blue teaser TBD</teaser>
    <body><![CDATA[<p>
Analysts face hard problems on a regular basis, but interacting with complete geospatial collections at scale is a technological challenge that recent innovations have proven to overcome.  This presentation will demonstrate the use of GeoWave to interact with a massive spatio-temporal data set -- 7 years of NYC taxi trips -- quickly capturing trends that are likely applicable to today and tomorrow’s traffic patterns.
</p>
      ]]></body>
  </session>
  <session>
    <time>13:50</time>
    <room_id>1</room_id>
    <title>Observing the Whole Earth, Every Day</title>
    <teaser>Rich Leshner from Planet Labs will discuss the company's mission to image the entire earth, every day.</teaser>
    <body><![CDATA[
<p>Rich Leshner from Planet Labs will discuss the company's mission to put in excess of one hundred small satellites in orbit to image the whole Earth, every day, and to make what we see and what we learn about change on our planet visible, accessible, and actionable.</p>
      ]]></body>
  </session>
  <session>
    <time>13:50</time>
    <room_id>2</room_id>
    <title>Geospatial Big Data</title>
    <teaser>Mark Giaconia, Director of Insight Platform Solutions at DigitalGlobe details Big Data initiatives at DigitalGlobe.</teaser>
    <body><![CDATA[
<p>DigitalGlobe has a 90 PB archive of high resolution, multispectral satellite imagery. This imagery can produce insights that help solve many problems, but in order to solve big problems you need a platform that can run algorithms and supporting image enrichment at scale. My briefing will talk about some of the challenges with GBD, as well as a description of our platform capability.</p>
      ]]></body>
  </session>
  <session>
    <time>14:15</time>
    <room_id>1</room_id>
    <title>Embracing Open Source for Real -- Deploying, Enhancing, and Developing OSS in the Federal Government</title>
    <teaser>Ben Tuttle, Project Scientist at NGA shares experiences developing and using open source technologies at a federal agency.</teaser>
    <body><![CDATA[<p>Open source software has long been used by government agencies with great
success and significant cost and capability benefits. However, it has also
long been misunderstood and deploying, enhancing or developing OSS has been
a significant challenge at times. Recently the NGA has begun to fully
embrace OSS and break down some of these barriers leading to increased
efficiencies, improved capabilities, and better engagement with the OSS
community. We will talk about how this happened, the benefits to the
government and the OSS community, as well as the agency GitHub account where
government developed code is being released back to the public under OSS
licenses.  </p>
      ]]></body>
  </session>
  <session>
    <time>14:15</time>
    <room_id>2</room_id>
    <title>Present and future for Mapstory</title>
    <teaser>Chris Tucker, CEO and Chairman of The MapStory Foundation provides an update on the current state and future of MapStory.</teaser>
    <body><![CDATA[Chris Tucker, CEO and Chairman of The MapStory Foundation provides an update on the current state and future of MapStory.]]></body>
  </session>
  <session>
    <time>14:40</time>
    <room_id>1</room_id>
    <title>Panel Discussion: State of Mapping in Government</title>
    <teaser>Panelists from USGS, Department of Agriculture, Department of State, and Peace Corps discuss the current state of mapping in Government.</teaser>
    <body><![CDATA[
<p>The panel will discuss what digital geo capabilities are needed across government agencies. In government, we have people who are at the top of the field often in agencies like NASA, NOAA, and USGS, and others who are not using digital technologies at that level, creating an uneven geo workforce. How can the federal government support upgrading our mapping and digital geo capabilities across the federal government? What are the options, challenges, and key priority projects that should be considered?</p>
<p>Panelists:</p>
<ul>
<li>Sophia B Liu (U.S. Geological Survey, Mendenhall Postdoc Fellow) - Moderator</li>
<li>Stephen Lowe (U.S. Department of Agriculture Geospatial Information Officer)</li>
<li>Tom Gertin (State Department, GIS Specialist)</li>
<li>Courtney Clark (Peace Corps, Innovation Fellow)</li>
</ul>
      ]]></body>
  </session>
<!-- ************************ BREAK TIME ****************** -->
  <session>
    <time>15:20</time>
    <room_id>3</room_id>
    <title>Break</title>
    <teaser>Refreshments served outside the hall of service.</teaser>
    <body><![CDATA[<p>Refreshments served in the hall of service.</p>
      ]]></body>
  </session>
<!-- ************************ BREAK TIME ****************** -->
  <session>
    <time>15:35</time>
    <room_id>1</room_id>
    <title>Lightning talks</title>
    <teaser>A series of short talks on important topics and initiatives.</teaser>
    <body><![CDATA[
<p>Do you have something important to share? Do a lightning talk at FedGeoDay to spread the word. Contact andrea dot ross at eclipse at org.</p> 
<ul>
  <li><strong>How Open Methods are Changing What You Pay for Geospatial Services</strong> by Eddie Pickle, Managing Director Open Source Programs at Radiant Blue</li>
  <li><strong>Sparkifying MapAlgebra</strong> by Ryan Smith, US Government Tech Solutions Team</li>
  <li><strong>Hootenanny, Creating an Open Source Conflation Engine</strong> by Josh Sisskind, Staff Software Development Engineer at DigitalGlobe</li>
  <li><strong>PostgreSQL 9.5, Features and Certification</strong> by Stephen Frost, CTO at Crunchy Data Solutions</li>
  <li><strong>You Too Can Do Vector Tiles with GeoServer</strong> by Tom Ingold, VP of Product at Boundless</li>
</ul>
      ]]></body>
  </session>
<!-- ************************ RECEPTION ****************** -->
  <session>
    <time>17:00</time>
    <room_id>4</room_id>
    <title>Reception</title>
    <teaser>Join us for a drink and opportunity to network.</teaser>
    <body><![CDATA[<p>Join us for a drink and opportunity to network after the conference. We'll provide coordinates soon.</p>
      ]]></body>
  </session>
<!-- ************************ RECEPTION ****************** -->

</schedule>
